<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to Vox cleri, &amp;c. examining the reasons against making any alterations and abatements, in order to a comprehension and shewing the expediency thereof.</title>
            <author>Payne, William, 1650-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56736</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P896</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36661</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15866834</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15866834</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104640</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56736)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104640)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1154:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to Vox cleri, &amp;c. examining the reasons against making any alterations and abatements, in order to a comprehension and shewing the expediency thereof.</title>
                  <author>Payne, William, 1650-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Brabazon Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 36.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bristol Public Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707. --  Vox cleri.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104640:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO <hi>Vox Cleri,</hi> &amp;c. EXAMINING The <hi>REASONS</hi> againſt making any <hi>Alterations</hi> and <hi>Abatements,</hi> In order to <hi>A Comprehenſion,</hi> AND Shewing the EXPEDIENCY thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Brabazon Aylmer,</hi> at the Three Pigeons againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:104640:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO <hi>Vox Cleri,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:104640:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104640:3"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO Vox Cleri, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE Author of <hi>Vox Cleri</hi> writes as if he were Clerk or Secretary to the Convocation, and ſo delivered the ſenſe of that whole venerable Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; for why elſe does he give ſuch a Title to his Book, to amuſe the World, and bring a ſcandal upon the Clergy, as if they were generally of his mind: and yet he tells us <hi>that nothing has been propoſed to them:</hi> ſo that they have not yet declared their minds, nor had an opportunity to doe ſo: and, I think, he has done them a great deal of injury, firſt, to ſuppoſe, and then, tell all the World, that they are againſt Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and Abatements in ſome indifferent matters for the ſake of that Peace and Union which is the deſire, and ſhould be the endeavour, of every good man.</p>
            <p>I ſhall be very unwilling to believe ſo ill of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiſe and worthy men, that they are againſt ſuch a Deſign, ſo much for the honour of God, the good of Religion in general, the Peace of the Kingdom, and the Intereſt of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:104640:4"/>
I cannot think that any man in cool and ſober thoughts can be againſt it, unleſs he be tranſported with ſome fit of anger, or which is as outragious, of eloquence; and then ſuch a raſh ſaying as, <hi>Nolumus mutare leges Angliae,</hi> may come out without reaſon, and ought to be forgiven among friends: but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the words chimed in a Speech to the Tune of <hi>Chriſt-church-bells,</hi> yet they were as ſenſeleſs and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent as this Authour's quotation out of <hi>Solomon</hi> on the Banner of his Book, <hi>Meddle not with them that are given to change;</hi> which would have ſerved the Quaker as well againſt changing his old cloaths as the deſign and buſineſs they are brought for: but if there had been no changes ſince <hi>Solomon</hi>'s time, nor ſince the Barons, in the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> we had been in a very primitive, but not quite ſo good a ſtate as at preſent.</p>
            <p>But this Gentleman ſeems to be under ſome great fear as well as anger, <hi>as if he were to be executed at the will of the rabble:</hi> What he has done I cannot tell, but he ſeems for ſome reaſon or other to be afraid to go home; he complains, <hi>he has not the privilege of other Malefactours, which all Law and Equity gives them of making a defence, eſpecially when their reputation, their livelyhoods, and even their lives are concerned;</hi> ſo that he ſeems to be under ſome dread and terrour that has ſcared him, not out of his lively hood or his life, I hope, but of ſomething elſe, I fear, that makes him write as he does; for he contradicts himſelf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in the ſame line, and owns that ſeveral times in a good mood which he writes all along againſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He and the Clergy in his Neighbourhood are very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable,</hi> he ſays, <hi>to part with ſeveral Ceremonies, and to ſubmit to many Alterations for the Peace of the Church
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104640:4"/>and Satisfaction of ſober Diſſenters</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">p. 1.</note>. Yet he muſters up all the reaſons he can againſt this; and his whole Book is writ againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The end of the Commiſſion is,</hi> he ſays, <hi>to take away all occaſions of difference for the future, as well as reconciling all their Majeſties ſubjects at preſent. A Bleſſing! this to be ſeriouſly endeavoured by all perſons, but rather to be hoped for than expected</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">p. 17.</note>. If to be ſeriouſly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by all perſons, why does he all he can againſt any ſuch endeavours?</p>
            <p>In another place<note n="(c)" place="margin">p. 26.</note> 
               <hi>I do here proteſt that were it not that the Diſſenters have given us an Aſſurance that though theſe and many other alterations ſhould be made, it would give them no ſatisfaction, nor bring them into our Communion, I would uſe all the intereſt I have for ſuch Alterations; and for that end alſo part with many other Ceremonies.</hi> I cannot believe the Diſſenters have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him any ſuch aſſurance, if they have, I hope he knows them better than to truſt them; but how is this reconcileable with what he ſo often harps upon? that, <hi>if they did come in, it would make a worſe ſchiſm in the Church, and ſo be more miſchievous than that out of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It cannot be a crime,</hi> ſays he very angrily, <hi>not to doe that which is both againſt the Law of the Land and the dictates of their own Conſciences:</hi> by the bye, I would fain know where that Law of the Land or thoſe dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates of Conſcience are to be found that forbid a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation to make Alterations?</p>
            <p>But in the ſame line he goes on, and ſays, <hi>It is not a crime for a man not to doe what none as yet hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of him to doe?</hi> how does he then know that 'tis both againſt the Law of the Land and the dictates of their own Conſciences?</p>
            <p>Something therefore ſeems to have injured this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104640:5"/>Gentleman's memory and reaſon, and his imagination ſeems to be diſturbed with fears of the Rabble, or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body's having ſome ſtrange deſign upon him for being againſt Alterations; and therefore he draws in the dark at all adventures, and ſtands upon his guard, and throws about him, <hi>it being a thing natural,</hi> he tells us, <hi>for a man to defend himſelf, there being no living creature ſo void of ſenſe as not to avoid another that attempts to deſtroy him, and every worm will turn upon him that will tread on it; and if an innocent perſon chance to injure another that injuriouſly aſſaults him, he is always held guiltleſs, as having done it</hi> Se defendendo.</p>
            <p>Why really I pity this Gentleman's caſe, if it be thus with him, for one would think he were in ſome great pain and peril, but we have reaſon to be angry with thoſe that have thus aſſrighted him, for otherwiſe we had had a better Book, or, which had been as well, none at all.</p>
            <p>That terrible word <hi>Latitudinarian</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">p. 6.</note> has ſcared him I doubt, and 'tis almoſt as dreadfull as <hi>Vercin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentorix;</hi> and ſome timorous old men can hardly ſpeak or hear it without trembling; they imagine ſome Monſter by it, of a mighty ſwallow and wide capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, having both a Church and a Conventicle, if not a Pope in its belly, tearing and devouring the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, mangling and altering the Liturgy, ſnarling and biting at Epiſcopacy, and <hi>gaping for the Preferments which other men have ſignally deſerved, and are legally poſſeſſed of:</hi> Now ſuch a creature as this may be in ſome void ſpace of a Map, or of an old Man's head, but no where elſe that I know of. But I ſuppoſe this new Sect or Hereſie are for making Alterations, and therefore our Authour is ſo angry with it, and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to confute it; and ſince he and his Neighbours in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104640:5"/>the Countrey are ſo greatly pleaſed with Dr. <hi>Jane</hi>'s be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing choſen Prolocutor<note n="(b)" place="margin">p. 1.</note> perhaps this may bring him to himſelf and put him into a good humour: and I dare ſay, this Doctor's worthy Competitour was ſo little concerned, that rather than ſpoil this, he would give it up, and let them have the comfort of believing the other choſe by a great and even double Majority, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever falſe that was, though it be put into the Acts of this learned Synod collected by our Authour, in order I ſuppoſe to be joined with the next Edition of the Councils, where may be ſome miſtakes, and ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions too as great as in this, though ſcarce in any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the Presbyters did ſo bravely hold their own, and ſtand it out againſt their Biſhops; ſo that I reckon the point is already gained which he blames one of the Letters for requeſting, <hi>That Presbytery may be reſtored to its ancient privilege, and permitted to ſhare in all Acts belonging to their ſtation</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">p. 33.</note>. But I am afraid ſome of thoſe <hi>Latitudinarian</hi> or <hi>Smectymnuan</hi> Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>that are ſtill among us, but are not of us</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">p. 34.</note>, have not ſo much reſpect and reverence for their Biſhops as they ought to have.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I forbear,</hi> ſays our Authour, <hi>to call Names</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Ibid.</note>, after he had uſed the moſt invidious ones he could think of; and I ſuppoſe we had had <hi>Janites</hi> and <hi>Tillotſonians,</hi> but that the one ſounded very little and pitifully, and the other <hi>would make up as terrible a word</hi> almoſt as that of <hi>Latitudinarians;</hi> but to oblige him for ever, and to make him amends for all that is in this Paper, let the immortal name of <hi>Longitudinarians</hi> hereafter belong to them, for about twenty reaſons more than can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for the other; I mean to thoſe who are for no Alterations or Abatements for the ſake of Peace and Reconciliation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:104640:6"/>
I own this is a matter of Prudence, and the good or evil of it depends upon circumſtances, ſo that wiſe and good men may have different apprehenſions about it and may not be all of the ſame mind, but our Author's Reaſons do no way ſatisfie me that this is not fit to be done, nor does he anſwer, to my thinking, what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have offered for it.</p>
            <p>I intend to argue the Point plainly and briefly with him, and then to prevent all Heretical pravity of a long name, <hi>Omnia Eccleſiae Judicio ſubmitto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then, Thoſe wiſe men out of the Weſt, his Neighbours in the Countrey,<note place="margin">p. 2.</note> 
               <hi>think it very reaſonable that ſuch as are aggrieved ſhould make their application to the Convocation;</hi> and do they think this will doe? why really yes, being in good humour themſelves, and the Convocation being ſo too, which is always to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, our Author <hi>doubts not that ſuch of the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as will be ſatisfied with what in reaſon and conſcience may be granted, that they would be gratified, and a good agreement made, for all agree, according to our Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that ſuch Ceremonies as concern Diſcipline and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, may upon juſt cauſes be altered and changed;</hi> as good natured as can be! ſurely then 'tis but meer Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whether the Diſſenters ſhould firſt ask or the Church give without asking; and to me now it looks better and more for the Churches honour and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that That ſhould give terms to the Diſſenters rather than the Diſſenters give or propoſe terms to the Church. Our Author too is much of the ſame mind in this, and I believe I ſhall ſhew him that he is more of my mind in moſt things than he knows or thinks he is; for <hi>Is it neceſſary,</hi> ſays he in another place, <hi>that a Church which hath authority to judge for it ſelf, what is decent and orderly, ſhould ſubject her ſelf to the judgment of her
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104640:6"/>Members to determine for her or themſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>what is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and expedient and what is not:</hi> and a little before that, <hi>Is it neceſſary that a Parent ſhould yield to a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient Child upon his own unreaſonable terms?</hi> No ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let the Parent wiſely and by fair means bring the ſtubborn Child off from its diſobedience if it be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, without the Childs offering terms whether reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable or unreaſonable.</p>
            <p>I believe our Author and his Countrey Neighbours would not have took it ſo well of the King, nor have been ſo quick and forward in addreſſing to him as ſome others were, had he called an Aſſembly of Diſſenters to treat with the Convocation and have propoſed terms to it; beſides, what if the Church be wiſer than the Diſſenters, and can better judge what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions are ſit for them than they themſelves? It ſeems more proper for Governours to preſcribe to the governed than the contrary; the Preface to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer ſays, <hi>It is but reaſonable that on weighty and important conſiderations, according to the exigency of times and occaſions, ſuch Changes and Alterations may be made</hi> as to thoſe that are in places of Authority <hi>ſhould ſeem neceſſary or expedient.</hi> This our Author quotes too on this head, but does not mind it as he ought. If he conſiders it a little better, he will plainly diſcern that the Church thinks it reaſonable to make Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſometimes as ſhe thinks ſit, whether the Diſſenters propoſe or agree in them or not, and 'tis well if the whole of this doe not ſeem to him a kind of Latitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narian Principle crept into the Church, which ought to be altered, though nothing elſe.</p>
            <p>But 2. <hi>They think it reaſonable that the end ſhould be conſidered, before the means be reſolved on.</hi> This is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſage and grave, and becoming their Countrey wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104640:7"/>which does nothing in vain, never brews Ale without ſomebody to drink it, nor never ſets a Hen but to breed Chickens; according to that Logical Axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>om which they ha'n't quite forgot, <hi>Finis primum in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectu.</hi> I ſuppoſe they mean here what they tell us in other places, <hi>to what purpoſe will it be to make Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the ſake of Diſſenters, when it will ſignifie nothing? Cui bono?</hi> to take the ſtrength of it in a drachm of Latin;<note place="margin">p. 5.</note> 
               <hi>to what end ſhould any Alterations be made, when they themſelves have ſo plainly declared that they will not be ſatisfied?</hi> for they were not ſo by the 600 Alterations in 1661, nor by the Propoſals of D. <hi>Stilling-ſleet:</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and the <hi>Healing Attempt</hi> propoſe ſtrange things, ſo that <hi>Is it neceſſary we ſhould part with any thing to them whom we have reaſon to ſuſpect that they will not leave craving till they have all?</hi> And, <hi>We think we have a moral aſſurance, that whatever Conceſſions the Convocation ſhall make with ſafety to themſelves will not only be deſpiſed but caſt back as filth in our faces, not only with a</hi> Quis Requiſivit, <hi>but with a</hi> Pudet haec op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probria vobis,<note place="margin">p. 2.</note> 
               <hi>as if our manner of publick Worſhip were ſo corrupt that we were aſhamed of it, and were convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of a neceſſity to purge it.</hi> Here I have pickt up and gathered all the ſcattered Arguments on this Head, and twiſted them all together with the greateſt ſtrength, even with the ſhreds of <hi>Latine</hi> belonging to them which help mightily to bind 'em; but I muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looſe them a little to give particular Anſwers to them.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, I doubt not but ſome of the Diſſenters are as ſtiff and peeviſh as other ſort of men, and will be as hardly brought to come in upon Alterations as others are brought to make them; I am very ſenſible of the inflexible and indeed unchriſtian ſpirit that is in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104640:7"/>many of the Fanaticks, but this I muſt ſay for them, they have not engroſſed it wholly to themſelves, nor are the onely men that are unwilling to be brought to Peace and Union upon any tolerable terms, or that refuſe to have it upon any but their own. I doubt not, nay I have moral Aſſurance that a great many of the beſt and wiſeſt Diſſenters would come in upon ſome few Alterations, ſuch as I think no wiſe and good Church-man would refuſe to them, for that end, ſuch as altering the Subſcription, and the like Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals made by that great man, the preſent Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> whoſe wiſedom and learning fits him to be univerſal Biſhop of the Chriſtian Church, if there were to be ſuch an one, and would ſerve him inſtead of Infallibility; Had there been ſuch an opportunity as there is now of confirming thoſe Propoſals of his by Convocation and Parliament, I queſtion not but we ſhould long before this have ſeen the happy effect of them; for though ſome angry men draw up Pleas for Non-conformity, as Lawyers draw up Bills of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or Indictment, which they ſtuff out with a world of hideous and dreadfull things for forms ſake and to pleaſe their Clyents; yet they mean not much by them in good earneſt, and a few things which they demand and principally inſiſt on would ſatisfie and content them.</p>
            <p>There were private and particular Reaſons which hindred the full effect of the Alterations in 61, but yet the number of thoſe who conformed upon them exceeded I doubt not and was much greater than the Alterations themſelves; and were the number ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo little which were gained by this means, yet it renders thoſe who ſtand out more inexcuſable, and vindicates the Church without any detriment to it,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104640:8"/>for it loſes nothing of what is ſubſtantial and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to its well-being, but onely ſome little things which are not worth keeping, when they keep out Peace and Union.</p>
            <p>I am not for pulling down the Pillars of the Church to enlarge it, nor am I for letting in thoſe at one door who will drive out either Epiſcopacy or Liturgy at the other, without one of which there cannot, I think, be due Chriſtian government, nor due Chriſtian wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip without the other. But I ſuppoſe we may take down an old Eſcutcheon, or ſweep down an old Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>web or two, or ſet up a new Gallery, or whiten the old Walls,<note place="margin">p. 35.</note> or the like, <hi>without taking down beam after beam, and after a leſs ſtone a greater, till the whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick be like to fall:</hi> and I believe the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> would ſtand as well though <hi>Tobit</hi> and all the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrypha</hi> were taken out of the Kalendar, and ſome Ceremonies out of the Rubrick, which do no more conduce to the ſupport or to the ornament of it, than thoſe odd figures which we ſee in ſome old buildings, that to unskilfull people look as if they bore a great weight, when nothing really lyes upon them, and which any man would take down, if they kept his good friends and neighbours from coming to his houſe.</p>
            <p>I cannot ſee how theſe ſmall Alterations in things owned to be indifferent and alterable as the Church ſhall think meet, ſhould be made any reflexion upon it, as our Authour fears, <hi>that they will be caſt back as filth in our faces, as if our manner of publick worſhip were ſo corrupt that we were aſhamed of it, and were convinced of a neceſſity to purge it.</hi> I do not remember that any of the Diſſenters who have writ againſt the Church ſince 61. though they have raked up all the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104640:8"/>objections that zeal and anger could miniſter or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, did ever make uſe of this, or throw thoſe 600 Alterations which were then made in its teeth; if they had, it had ſhewn onely greater perverſeneſs and unjuſtifiable wrangling after they were gone, though they did not at all corrupt our worſhip whilſt they remained, nor make it at all unlawfull; but an obſolete word may be changed for one in uſe, and an expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on altered for the better in a Prayer, and a tranſlation mended that is not ſo exact in many places, and an 100 ſuch alterations made, and yet no condemning our ſelves <hi>for any corruptions that we were aſhamed of and were convinced of a neceſſity to purge out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, theſe Conceſſions which we make for Peace ſake are not ſo much from the neceſſity of the things themſelves, as from the weakneſs and ignorances, the prejudices and miſtakes of others, and the Church uſes her Authority as all wiſe Governours doe, and as God himſelf did in compliance to the temper and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities of thoſe who are ſubject to it, and with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the greater ends of Religion and Piety, Peace and Charity, which ſhe prefers to Sacrifice or any the Externals of Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the Diſſenters will not leave craving till they have all; Give an Inch and they'll take an Ell.</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 51.</note> Well fare an old Proverb, but that which ſpoiles it in this caſe is, that 'tis older than 61. or than any Alterations of our Liturgy then or before, or perhaps than the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation it ſelf, and it was as true all along, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as well againſt all that deſired any Alterations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or ſince, and yet 'tis hard to get this, and <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon's, Meddle not with thoſe that are given to change,</hi> out of ſome mens heads who have no great Latitude or Profundity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104640:9"/>
If the Church makes a conceſſion to ſome perſons to have their Children baptized without the ſign of the Croſs, muſt ſhe therefore yield alſo to <hi>Anabaptiſm</hi> and to their humour who will not have Children bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized at all? If ſhe ſhould allow ſome to take the Communion without Kneeling, muſt ſhe yield to the Quakers who are for no Communion nor no poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Ordinances at all? If ſhe think not fit to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the dreadfull Sentence of Excommunication for ſmall matters, muſt ſhe yield to the <hi>Eraſtians,</hi> who would take it quite away? This is like the fear of the Lunatick, that if he let the Barber cut off his Beard, he would cut off his Head too, and therefore was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways againſt ſuch a dangerous Reformation of his Face.</p>
            <p>I am not of that witty Diſſenter's mind who was for taking away all the Ceremonies, with a fine ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, Religion is in a Conſumption, and therefore you muſt cut off its Hair; I doe not think that is the way to recover it, nor yet to give it <hi>Aſſes</hi> Milk, though that might agree better with ſome Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons than more ſubſtantial food and better Inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Let the Diſſenters crave as long as they will, I hope the Church can deny as ſtifly as they crave unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. And I am perfectly of our Author's mind, though he had not Dr. <hi>Beveridge</hi>'s Authority for it, <hi>That to alter the Epiſcopal Government, to take the Power of Ordination from Biſhops and place it in the hands of Prsbyters, to take away a well ordered Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy and bring in extemporary Prayers for publick worſhip, to give every Miniſter a Jurisdiction and Power of Excommunication, and many other things; without which ſome</hi> grave <hi>Diſſenters will not be comprehended; is more than the Learned Doctor, or any Doctor in</hi> England, <hi>will
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104640:9"/>grant,</hi> or deſire to be granted to them. But ſurely our <hi>grave</hi> Author knows that the beſt and wiſeſt, if not the <hi>graveſt</hi> Diſſenters, who are for a National Church, whoſe Intereſt is moſt conſiderable, and whoſe Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit has done the moſt to keep up Non-conformity, that theſe will be comprehended with ſomething leſs than what he ſpeaks of; and I doe not doubt but the bringing in of thoſe into the Communion of the Church would tend greatly to ſtrengthen its Intereſt and the Intereſt of the whole Proteſtant Religion, and to break that lamentable Schiſm and Separation which weakens both, and gives our Popiſh Adverſaries the greateſt Advantage againſt us, and which I hope they and we are both weary of.</p>
            <p>If there are ſome Diſſenters ſo wild that they can never be folded, nor brought into any ſettled Flock or Communion, though I would not have them hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and run down like wild Beaſts, and therefore I am not altogether ſo much againſt the Toleration as our Author is, yet I think it would have done more good, had the Comprehenſion took place before it, that ſo the Church might have gathered firſt, before the Separation, and not have been left to <hi>glean</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>that</hi> has made its full harveſt.</p>
            <p>But our Author, I perceive, is as much afraid at one time that the Diſſenters ſhould come in as he is at another that they would not; <hi>And what,</hi> ſays he,<note place="margin">p. 10.</note> 
               <hi>if ſome leading Presbyterians be by our Alterations let into the Church, and advanced to ſuch Preferments as they hope for; what ſecurity have we that they will not promote Diviſions in the Church, more dangerous than the Schiſm they made by Separation from us? A ſecret E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy within the walls of a well fortified City is more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous than an open Foe in the Field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:104640:10"/>
How then is this conſiſtent not onely with our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's Opinion but moſt ſerious Proteſtation in another place,<note place="margin">p. 26.</note> 
               <hi>I do here proteſt that, were it not that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters have given us an Aſſurance that though theſe and many other Alterations ſhould be made, it would give them no ſatisfaction, nor bring them into our Communion, I would uſe all the Intereſt I have for ſuch Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and for that end alſo part with many of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</hi> I ſhould think there were a contradiction in theſe two places, and that they would ſall out were they not ſome Pages from one another; but ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all things are not right in our Author's Head who has two ſuch different thoughts at the ſame time, but perhaps 'tis but a mere ſtruggle between the fleſh and the ſpirit, if they ſhould be let in and get Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they might keep him and others out; and if they would come in, the good of it is ſo viſible upon many accounts, that a man's reaſon cannot but deſire it and promote it; ſo that there is a natural tenderneſs and moderation on one ſide of his head (which I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is the ſofteſt) towards Diſſenters, but on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide there is a moſt ſtiff hatred and averſion to them; but which of theſe ſhall take place when there is occaſion, muſt depend very much upon the Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Moon and the Aſpect of the Planets.</p>
            <p>I conſeſs I am not for letting in Enemies into the Church, but ſurely by coming in they become Friends and ceaſe to be Enemies, for then they owne the Churches Communion and ſubmit to its Authority, and inſtead of ſtanding out they come in and joyn with it: now if any will do this I know no Church is ſo well fortified as to keep them out, nor is there any way to diſtinguiſh ſuch ſecret enemies from its ſecret friends; but 'tis a Secret ſome men have to find out
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104640:10"/>diſtinctions and make differences between thoſe of the ſame Communion, which is very pernicious and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous; whoever comes up to the Churches terms of Communion and to full Conformity with it, are by no means to be counted ſecret enemies, when if this does not ſhew them to be open friends, every man may as well be ſuſpected to be a ſecret enemy.</p>
            <p>But if theſe Diſſenters when they are taken into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of the Church ſhould, like treacherous Vipers, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſting their Mother, or gnaw through her Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, and attempt all they can to doe miſchief to her, how ſhall they be able to effect this, and what way ſhall they accompliſh it? Will they ſet up Conventicles in their own Pariſhes and draw away people from the Communion of the Church of which themſelves are Miniſters? or will they preach or write againſt thoſe Ceremonies or other things to which they have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly conformed? it would be ſtrange if they ſhould doe this, but perhaps they may doe it another way; They may be choſen Convocation-men, and ſo have opportunity to oppoſe and confront the Biſhops; and though they ſhould pretend great reverence for the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopal Order and Authority, yet may ſlight and contemn it as much as open Fanaticks when it does not ſuit with their humour, and like bug <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> love <hi>to have the preheminence</hi> above it. Now if I find they doe this and make a dangerous diviſion in the Church by this means, I ſhall think 'em a ſort of Rebellious Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that deſerve to be turned out of the Church not as ſecret but open enemies to the Biſhops, and that they have forgot a paſſage or two in <hi>Ignatius</hi>'s Epiſtles, and therefore I ſhall be very much tempted to be of our Author's mind to have thoſe read hereafter in our Churches for the ediſication and reproof of ſuch aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Presbyters.<note place="margin">p. 26.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:104640:11"/>
I know but one Objection more that can be pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked up out of your Author's fardle of <hi>important rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> againſt any Alterations, for they lye there like ſmall wares in a Pedler's pack, neither ſorted nor par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled, but confuſedly jumbled together; as I ſuppoſe, they lye in his head: but the onely remaining Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection that I can find, and I am ſure I have done him juſtice and given full ſtrength to any thing that loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked like a reaſon,<note place="margin">p. 6.</note> is this, <hi>That by making Alterations, the Church will run the hazard of offending a greater number of more conſiderable perſons than they are like to gratiſie thereby.</hi> And he gives it in as objected for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly againſt the Bill for Comprehenſion,<note place="margin">p. 11.</note> 
               <hi>That as ſome might come in, ſo others that were in our Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion might take offence by the Alterations, and deteſt it, and ſeeing our frequent changes in ſome things, they might ſuppoſe that there is nothing certain among us; and, from the many diſputes about our Liturgy, proceed to queſtion our Articles; and at laſt fall off to the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>which they ſaw more conſtant to their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now they muſt have a very mean opinion of the Churches Prudence, and give very little deference to her Authority, that ſhall be offended at her making ſuch Alterations in things that ſhe always declared <hi>are in their own nature indifferent and alterable,</hi> and which ſhe has reſerved to her ſelf a power to alter <hi>according to the exigency of times and occaſions,</hi> and upon ſuch prudential reaſons as ſhe ſhall think fit, of which ſhe is alone the moſt proper Judge: for, as our Authour ſays, <hi>The People ought not to preſcribe to the Church in ſuch things, but the Church to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They muſt therefore be no very dutifull and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Sons of the Church who ſhall not be ſatisfied
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104640:11"/>with ſuch Alterations as ſhe ſhall think fit to make for the ends of peace and concord, and the allaying thoſe heats and diviſions that are among us.</p>
            <p>They muſt have a very wrong and ſuperſtitious opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the outward Rites and Ceremonies and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantials of Religion, who lay ſo much weight and ſtreſs upon them as to think that there is any great matter in them beſides their ſubſerviency to outward order and decency, or that they are ſo neceſſary to thoſe that the Divine Worſhip may not be performed as acceptably and reverently without ſome of them as with them.</p>
            <p>It is to be feared that ſuch weak perſons have not been ſufficiently inſtructed in the nature of things In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different when they are ſo zealous for thoſe above the weightier matters of Peace and Charity, to which they ought always to give way.</p>
            <p>If ſome zealous or deſigning men have drawn igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and well meaning perſons into a greater opinion and admiration of themſelves by ceremonious formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and overdoings, by unpreſcribed bowings and cringes, by proſtrations at the Euchariſt and the like inventions of their own, they have uſed the ſame ways that other Fanaticks have done to fill up their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations with gathering out of other Churches, by ſhews of greater piety and devotion, and have hereby broken the ſettled orders of the Church, and opened a gap for all the follies of an indiſcreet zeal and forward ſuperſtition, whereby ſome pious but not wiſe men have in all ages brought innumerable fopperies and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularities into the Church, to the great miſchief of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>But ſurely a Church that thinks it not neceſſary to bring men to a Religion by any ſuch ſuperſtitious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104640:12"/>but by more true and rational methods of a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and diſcreet Piety, and needs not to make uſe of any ſuch tricks and pious frauds to impoſe upon the folly and weakneſs of its Votaries, nor has any paltry and by ends to be ſerved by ſuch Religious Cheats ſhould put a timely ſtop to all ſuch ceremonial exceſſes, and honeſtly teach all its Members that Religion lies not in any ſuch ſhews or forms of Godlineſs, but in ſober and manly devotion and in a vertuous and good life.</p>
            <p>Now when men have ſuch a true notion of Religion, which the Church ought always to give them, and to correct all miſtakes to the contrary, there will be no great danger that they ſhould be much offended at the loſs or alteration of a few Rites or Ceremonies which are no more of the Eſſence of Religion than our Cloaths are of the Eſſence of a Man, who ſo long as he is decently habited according to the cuſtom of the Countrey, he may leave it to the Governours thereof to change the mode as they think fit.</p>
            <p>But above all folks commend me to thoſe in our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, <hi>who,</hi> our Author tells us, <hi>may take ſuch offence at our Alterations as to deſert us and fall off to the Church of</hi> Rome.<note place="margin">p. 11.</note> Theſe do well underſtand and have been well inſtructed in the Religion of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who can make no difference between baptizing with the Croſs, as a ſignal of Chriſtianity, and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it as an object of worſhip, between kneeling at the Sacrament and worſhipping the Hoſt; but however this is a terrible danger, if by bringing ſome oſt from Fanaticiſm, we ſhall be likely to make others Papiſts, which is ten times worſe; let us therefore ſee what reaſon our Author may have to fear this: <hi>Why ſeeing our frequent changes in ſome things they may ſuppoſe that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104640:12"/>there is nothing certain among us, and from the many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes about our Liturgy proceed to queſtion our Articles, and at laſt fall off to the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>which they ſaw more conſtant to their Principles.</hi> If they are for ſuch a conſtant Church as ſhall never make any Alterations, then indeed they muſt be for an Infallible one, and none bids at that but the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but yet ſtill ſhe has made very often great changes and altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in her Liturgies, and Ceremonies, and often cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and reformed her Breviaries and Miſſals; ſo that if this ſhall ſhake and ſtartle a man, and by ſeeing ſo many alterations about thoſe things in their Church, he ſhall ſuppoſe there is nothing more certain in that than in ours, I hope he will quickly come back again like a fool as he went. He muſt be a Member of no Church i'th' world, nor ever could have been ſince the beginning of Chriſtianity, who will deſert and leave it for this reaſon becauſe it has made frequent Alterations in its Liturgy and Ceremonies; and if a man will be ſo fickle and ſceptical as <hi>by ſeeing frequent changes in ſuch things to ſuppoſe there is nothing certain among us, and from ſome diſputes about Liturgies, queſtion the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of a Church, and at laſt fall to what is more conſtant in its Principles,</hi> he muſt e'en fall off from all Churches and from all Religion, and for the ſame reaſon from all living under Laws and Government, for there are diſputes and alterations about thoſe, and from eating and drinking too, for all men are not agreed in the ſame meat and drink or way of dreſſing it, nor have always thought fit to ſtick to one way of Brewing or Cookery.</p>
            <p>Thus I have fairly examined our Author's Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt making Alterations, and where there was any ſeeming weight in them, I have fully conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered it; where they were weak and ridiculous, I have
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104640:13"/>made bold to expoſe them, for the Book was put out, and fell into my hands in a time of merryment, and I was very curious to ſee what ſome folks could ſay for themſelves. I aſſure him, had he or his Neighbours in the Countrey ſhewed any good reaſons why they are ſo ſtiff againſt Alterations, that could have convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced me that they were prejudicial to Religion or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerviceable to the Church, I would have ſent him my thanks for, inſtead of an Anſwer to them, or would have done my beſt to have written a Panegyrick upon that Noble Motto, <hi>Nolumus mutare Leges</hi> Angliae, <hi>That</hi> after all is the onely mighty and irreſiſtable Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that remains to be anſwered in this matter; but I wont undertake it, ſince it has been done to my hands by all the Parliaments and all the Convocations in <hi>England</hi> ever ſince the Barons wars, unleſs by the preſent Convocation which has done nothing, whoſe mind we do not yet know, and till we doe, it may paſs for an infallible Council; for ſurely <hi>Vox Cleri</hi> is not the mouth of it; nor is our Author to be taken as the Churches Repreſentative or Procurator General, or to be allowed ſo many Proxies as ſhall make up a Houſe. But though he calls his Book <hi>Vox Cleri,</hi> yet <hi>Tuba Stentorophonica,</hi> Balaam's <hi>Aſs propheſying,</hi> or the like Title might have been as ſignificant and ſuited it as well.</p>
            <p>Having ſeen what he has to ſay on one ſide, I am now to conſider what has been or may be offered on the other, and what he has to ſay againſt them. The Reaſons for ſome Abatements and Alterations at this time are ſo plain and conſiderable, <hi>ſo great and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant,</hi> as ſhows the manifeſt expediency, if not neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of doing it, and our Author has ſo little to ſay againſt it, though he was bound to ſay what he could,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104640:13"/>that he has thereby done more to give up the cauſe and ſatisfie every impartial man about it, than if he had induſtriouſly pleaded for it; though I will not ſay as he does of one of the Letters, that <hi>a man would think this Writer to have been hired to betray the cauſe—by his weak and impertinent arguments for its Defence;</hi> for I believe our Author does honeſtly what he can, and I don't ſuſpect any treachery at all in his writing, unleſs it be between his Will and his Underſtanding, and I doubt the one does a little trick and impoſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the other; for were it not for his implacable aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and ill-will to the Fanaticks and Latitudinarians; I am very confident that his Reaſon is for Alterations and Abatements, by the little he has to ſay to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and to the obvious and important reaſons for them; and becauſe he himſelf ſo often and ſo expreſly declares for them in his good moods and lucid intervals.</p>
            <p>The firſt objection which he makes to himſelf, and which roſe up in his own thoughts, for 'tis not in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to any of the Letters, is this;<note place="margin">p. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Herein we may pleaſe the King, the Parliament, and a great part of the diſſenting Laity,</hi> which if it be true is very conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Now as to the latter, the diſſenting Laity, I don't know what to ſay to the great ones and the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tico's among them, who are for keeping up a Separate Party, as a Civil Faction in the State, whom they who are the Heads of it, and would make but an inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable figure without it, can manage upon occaſion, and have it ready raiſed and formed for their deſigns; and I doubt they will not be ſo well pleaſed to have this and therefore themſelves leſſened by leſſening the ſtrength and number of the Separation, as I hope the beſt and moſt honeſt of the Diſſenting Laity will, who are more concerned for the ſincere good of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104640:14"/>than carrying on Deſigns and Intrigues, who will no doubt follow and accompany their Leaders into the Church, as they went out with them.</p>
            <p>But this I hope will be ſo far from being an objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to our Author or any Church of <hi>England</hi> man, againſt Alterations and a Comprehenſion, that it muſt be a very ſtrong Argument for it, ſince 'tis the Schiſm and Separation in the Church that keeps up thoſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Factions in the State, which help to diſturb the civil peace and quiet of the Kingdom, and has been the cauſe of the greateſt confuſions in it; ſo that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is a lover of the Church or Kingdom muſt be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to have an end put to them, as far as is poſſible, that we may unite in one religious and civil Intereſt.</p>
            <p>As <hi>to the pleaſing the King and Parliament hereby,</hi> that I think is not to be doubted, ſince the Parliament addreſſed to the King for calling a Convocation, and the King was pleaſed thereupon to call one for this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry end and deſign, and to grant a Commiſſion, as has been uſual in the like caſe, to prepare things in order to it, ſo that 'tis to be feared, that ſome men who are no great friends to the preſent ſettlement and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, and who are upon ſome account angry and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, are at the bottom of all this heat and ſtiff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt Alterations, and who make uſe of others as Tools to work and hammer out their Deſigns by, or at leaſt to keep up a noiſe and diſturbance among us, as if great numbers were diſſatisfied becauſe they themſelves are ſo for private reaſons. Theſe men are mighty zealous againſt the Churches making any Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations in the <hi>Circumſtantials</hi> of Religion till the Court makes ſome Alterations in the <hi>Subſtantial</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of profit.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:104640:14"/>
I know we complain on all ſides of <hi>being made and uſed</hi> as Tools, as if this were the Fate of Churchmen, and Religion were only an Engine in their hands, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with the terrors of another world to doe Execution only in this: Our Author <hi>wiſhes he could leave his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Miniſter</hi> (who wrote one of the Letters) <hi>well in his wits to conſider whether he be not uſed as a Tool to deſtroy the eſtabliſhed Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 42.</note> 
               <hi>by ſome who think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves mighty Politicians.</hi> Nay he tells us, That the Authors of the two Letters <hi>may be Papiſts, who by ſuch Arts ſeek to divide that they may deſtroy us.</hi> Now this is the deepeſt Plot of the Papiſts, if it be one, that ever was laid to deſtroy and blow up the Church, and if thoſe who are for Alterations in order to unite Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants and ſtrengthen the Church are Tools in the hands of Papiſts or other Politicians to deſtroy it, the Church is in a lamentable condition, and muſt neceſſarily be deſtroyed both by its friends and its enemies too, and by thoſe ways, which in all appearance, tend moſt to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, and the Deſign is laid ſo ſecretly, and to be wrought ſo ſtrangely, that 'tis impoſſible to prevent it.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, 'tis plain and notorious matter of fact that ſome <hi>Great</hi> Diſcontented Lay-men, though not ſo <hi>Great</hi> as they would be, did manage ſeveral of our ſtiff men againſt Alterations: It was not ſo much behind the Curtain but the hands were ſeen if not the wires which moved the Puppets; beſides the diſſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Biſhops and Clergy who have not taken the Oaths, nor will own the preſent Government, had more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon thoſe who have ſworn to the preſent King and Queen, and moſt ſolemnly recognized them in the name of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> than could be expected that men of ſuch different Apprehenſions, and acting by ſuch different meaſures ſhould at this time have had.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104640:15"/>I am very ſorry for their Suſpenſion, but 'tis ſtrange they ſhould hereby have more Authority over their Clergy than they had before in a matter of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter moment and greater difficulty, and 'tis equal won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to me that ſome men who are ſo ſtiff in other things ſhould ſo ſoon forget their Promiſes, and others hardly remember their Oaths.</p>
            <p>That the King and Parliament will be greatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with the Clergy unleſs they conſent to ſome Alterations and Abatements in order to a legal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, is as much to be feared as 'tis certainly known that a Convocation was firſt deſired, and then ſummoned for this very purpoſe, as appears by the Addreſs of the Houſe of Commons, the King's Writ and Commiſſion, and his Letter to the Convocation, by which their minds are ſufficiently known and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for the doing the thing in general, though they left the particular manner of doing it to the Clergy themſelves. Now the King and Parliament are to be allowed very proper Judges of the expediency and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or prudential neceſſity of this, and therefore of adviſing and directing it, as the Clergy are the fitteſt to execute and accompliſh it, ſince 'tis a matter of a Religious and Eccleſiaſtical nature that belongs proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to them. Now then for them to be called together for this very purpoſe by the Deſire of Parliament and the Command of the King, and to tell 'em when they come that they think it not prudent but dangerous to meddle and doe any thing, is, as if the Preſident and College of Phyſicians ſhould adviſe that in ſuch a caſe ſuch an operation ſhould be performed, and ſend for the Surgeons of the Hall to doe it, but they ſhould tell 'em there was no need of it and they would not meddle. Where though the latter are more fit to perform
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104640:15"/>the Chyrurgical Operation, yet the other are as good and proper Judges that it is fit and expedient or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be done.</p>
            <p>But our Authour ſeems to deny that this will be pleaſing either to the King or Parliament, for four or five great and ſubſtantial Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>As to the King, his Majeſty hath devolved that Province to the Convocation and Parliament;</hi> as if the King were not pleaſed with any thing but what he does himſelf, and did not commit ſeveral things to be done by others which are very pleaſing to him. He hath devolved the Province of reducing <hi>Ireland</hi> to <hi>Shomberg</hi> and his Army, and yet no doubt but it will be very pleaſing to him; and he as much expects, and has given Commiſſion to doe the one as well as the other; and the happineſs of his Reign and the Peace of his Kingdom depend, though not equally, yet in great meaſure upon both; The King devolves the Province of raiſing Money to the parliament, and yet what is left to them and their Prudence to doe is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſary in it ſelf and very pleaſing to the King.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He hath declared his ſatisfaction as to the preſent Conſtitution.</hi> Several of the Clergy have declared theirs too, if I be not miſtaken, and ſomething far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the King has done or can doe, unleſs he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe and take Orders, and yet they would be migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily pleaſed with ſome Alterations for the good, as they think, of the Church and Religion, and the Peace of the Kingdom, not becauſe they are diſſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the preſent Conſtitution, though they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſome little things in it may be Altered and Amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; as our Authour, I believe, is not diſſatisfied with his dear Body and Carcaſs, but yet is willing now and then to amend and repair it for the better.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:104640:16"/>
3. <hi>He doth confirm his declared judgment by his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant practice in communicating with the Church as eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, and frequent promiſes to favour and protect it.</hi> The more reaſon hath the Church to oblige and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him in what he deſires and propoſes, and thereby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage him to be its more firm and hearty friend, as well as requite him for what he hath already done for it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>As to the Parliament, they do generally live in the Communion of the Church.</hi> Is living in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church then a certain Argument of being againſt Alterations? Surely our Authour lives in a very groſs Air, and his Head wants a little clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, or he would not talk at this rate.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Nothing can be obligatory but what ſhall be enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them whoſe conſent we are not aſſured of,</hi> i. e. by King and Parliament. Was any thing ever obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory as a Law of the Kingdom but what was ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted? Would he have the Convocation ſtay till it was ſo obligatory, and ſo enacted by the Civil Power, before they doe any thing? or can we ever be more aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of their Conſent to enact any thing than This?</p>
            <p>I paſs now to another Reaſon for making theſe Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and Abatements in order to a Comprehenſion; and that being one of our own making, it muſt be a great reproach to us to be againſt it at <hi>this time,</hi> when we promiſed and declared for it in <hi>another;</hi> I mean in the Biſhops Petition to King <hi>James,</hi> which was in the name of the whole Church and Clergy, who made it their own by conſenting to it and approving it, <hi>viz. That they wanted not due tenderneſs to Diſſenters, but were willing to come to ſuch a Temper as ſhould be thought fit when the matter ſhould be conſidered in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Convocation.</hi> What was the meaning of that? Was it to ſtand our ground and doe nothing at all,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104640:16"/>but be very ſtiff againſt all Alterations for the ſake of Diſſenters? No ſure; that was not the Tenderneſs nor the Temper they were willing to come to, but they muſt mean by it the very ſame thing that I am plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for, and this our Authour owns they did when <hi>he heartily wiſhes</hi> thoſe Biſhops <hi>were in a condition</hi> to perform their promiſe, <hi>even for the Diſſenters ſake</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">p. 41.</note>, and he denys not what his Adverſary had ſaid, that, <hi>he doubted not but they would agree to the Alterations that are deſired;</hi> and he acquieſces in the Judgment of another whom he writes againſt, <hi>That if nothing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable were deſigned, it might then have paſſed, and a firm eſtabliſhment enſued; for doubtleſs the calm tempers of thoſe Reverend Fathers would mightily have influenced their Sons</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">p. 17.</note>, ſome of the hotteſt of which mightily wanted ſuch a calm Influence.</p>
            <p>But now what becomes then of all their and our Author's wiſe and important Reaſons againſt making Alterations, as if the Church were to be deſtroyed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, as if theſe Conceſſions were only loſing of ground, and gaining nothing thereby, ſince none would come in upon them, but would rather be encouraged to crave more and more till they had got all, and would never be ſatisfied neither. All theſe muſt be given up, ſince they are all overruled by this promiſe and opinion of the Biſhops for ſurely <hi>They</hi> are not <hi>Tools,</hi> whatever others are, <hi>to deſtroy the eſtabliſhed Church, made uſe of by ſome who think themſelves mighty Politicians:</hi> nor are <hi>They</hi> to be compared to an unskilfull Architect, <hi>who hath undertaken to repair a good old Fabrick and make it better; but pulling down beam after beam, and after a leſſer ſtone a greater, till the whole Fabrick hath been like to fall; and then (what perhaps was deſigned at firſt) he perſwades the Owners that there is a neceſſity
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104640:17"/>wholly to deſtroy the old, and erect a new one upon better Foundations</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">p. 35.</note>. Neither are <hi>They</hi> of another Trade, as ſcandalous almoſt as that of being unskilfull Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tects, <hi>viz.</hi> of being <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Tinkers, who undertaking to mend one hole, do uſually make two or three</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">p. 45.</note>. Now all the wit and all the reaſon of theſe two Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons will fall upon the Biſhops as well as others ſince they were for the ſame thing, as our Author owns.</p>
            <p>What then can he ſay to this promiſe of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops? why, <hi>They are not in a condition to perform it now, if they were never ſo willing</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">p. 53.</note>. Is it not therefore fit to be done at all by thoſe who are in a condition, if they were willing? <hi>Ay but put the Biſhops in</hi> ſtatu quo <hi>and then ſee what they will doe.</hi> They may put themſelves into it when they pleaſe, but muſt not Promiſes be performed becauſe men are not in <hi>ſtatu quo?</hi> I take it to have been the Promiſe of the Church and Clorgy in general at that time, and not only of thoſe particular Biſhops, and ſo the Diſſenters and all men took it, who were extremely pleaſed and ſatisfied with it, but to have another <hi>Vox Cleri</hi> now ſpeaking quite contrary to what it did before, will be ſuch a Reproach to us as if the Church had a <hi>Double Tongue;</hi> as if fear did inſpire us with more good nature, than the greateſt mercy and bleſſing; as if a common danger could do more to bring us to Tenderneſs and good Temper than a common Deliverance. Surely our preſent Safety and Happineſs ſhould not make us forget the Vows we made in our Diſtreſs and Adverſity, as if they were only like the Vows of frighted Marriners in a Storm, which are broken and recalled when the Tempeſt is blown over and there is a calm and clear Sky. Was there not a kind of Solemn Proteſtation, a Tacit Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a General Reſolution at that time among all
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104640:17"/>thinking and ſober men, that if they were once freed from the Danger they were then in by the Common Enemy, who was ſtrengthned and had like to have ruined us by our Diviſions, that they would do all that was poſſible to cure and remedy them for the future, and come to good Terms, and fair Correſpondence, and Chriſtian Union with one another? and will not thoſe kind Promiſes, and good Words, and fair Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces we then made be looked upon as a meer trick, a ſhamefull colluſion, if we do not now make them good, when we have a fair opportunity and are called upon to doe ſo, and will give too juſt reaſon to others never to truſt us again, but for ever after to ſuſpect the Tenderneſs and the Temper, nay the Truth and the Juſtice as well as the Moderation of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> I ſay this with hearty and affectionate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern becauſe I think the Honour of it lies at ſtake, which I would bring ſome men, who ſeem to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned for it, ſeriouſly to conſider.</p>
            <p>What were <hi>the great and important Reaſons</hi> which moved the Biſhops to this kind Promiſe, to come to a Temper with the Diſſenters, (and which perſwade o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers at this time to the ſame thing) by making ſome Alterations and Abatements in things which they ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and we hold Indifferent, is ſo eaſie and obvious to diſcern, that he muſt be blinded with paſſion and zeal and bigottry who does not ſee them.</p>
            <p>The bitter animoſities, the uncharitable heart burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, the rancorous paſſions, the uncharitable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian temper which has been begot by our lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Schiſms and Diviſions, ſhould affect every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian heart with deep and ſenſible reſentments, and make us uſe all poſſible remedies that are likely to cure them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:104640:18"/>
The ſad evils and miſchiefs we have felt by keeping up a kind of Religious war ſo long in the Bowels of the Church and Kingdom, whereby we have treated one another as Enemies, and furiouſly contended on all ſides for matters of no great worth or moment (for in other things there were fair ſteps made towards an agreement in 1662.) ſhould diſpoſe us to make up a Peace upon reaſonable and fair terms, and rather give up a Ceremony or two be they never ſo ſignificant, than ſtill fight it out for ſuch poor trifles in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the greater things of Religion.</p>
            <p>The Advantage that is given at all times to Atheiſm, Irreligion and Profaneneſs, as well as ſometimes to Popery by our Diviſions, ſhould make every lover of God and Religion, not willing to ſacrifice either Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in general, or the Reformation in particular to an obſtinate zeal and humourſome ſtiffneſs for little things.</p>
            <p>Our love to the beſt Church in the World, and which needs fewer Alterations than any other Church whatſoever, ſhould make us do all we can to enlarge, beautifie and ſtrengthen it, and not venture a deſparate puſh to let its Enemies wait for a juncture to ruine it, when we may ſo eaſily ſecure it by bringing in the Presbyterians into its Communion by a very few Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, that will ſatisfie them and be no manner of loſs or injury to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Our love to our Countrey, and to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent peace and ſettlement of it, which nothing can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger but our fatal Diviſions, which tend to throw us back into the miſeries we have juſt eſcaped, and are therefore kept up and fomented by the wicked Policies of Diſcontented men, who infuſe jealouſies and varian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into others heads from their own private feuds and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104640:18"/>ſelf-intereſt, ſhould ſtrongly engage us to a fair union and accord with one another, and to the Deſign which I have been pleading for becauſe I think it will tend ſo much to promote it, and which few men, I hope, upon ſecond thoughts will be againſt. I ſhall leave it to their ſerious conſideration in the words of that learned and good man Dr. <hi>Beveridge,</hi> out of whoſe Sermon our Author would pick ſomething if he could to his purpoſe, but he conſiders not well what he writes himſelf, or what he tranſcribes out of him; theſe are the words as they are quoted by him, which are a good <hi>Summing</hi> up the matter at the laſt. <hi>This only I dare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that if it be neceſſary to reduce wandring Sheep into Chriſt's Flock, if to take off ſcruples from the minds of weak Brethren, if to allay hatred, appeaſe anger, and as much as may be to ſuppreſs all Diſſenſions concerning Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, if to recall Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline to its primitive Vigour, if to Defend and Eſtabliſh the beſt Church in the world againſt the Aſſaults of Men and Devils; if theſe things ſeem neceſſary to any man, it will alſo ſeem neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to that man to admit ſuch Changes as he is perſwaded will conduce to ſuch ends</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">p. 8.</note>.</p>
            <p>I have now done with the Cauſe, and leave it to any man who reads his Book and this, whether any thing looſely and ſcatteringly offered in the one, has not had its full force fairly given it, and as full and complete an Anſwer returned to it by the other. But I have a word or two of Friendly Advice to our Author before I have done with him as a parting civility.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt then, I would adviſe him not to ſpeak ſo loudly and openly againſt the Toleration, for fear the Parliament ſhould hear him, as he does upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, telling us <hi>the Reaſons againſt it are irrefragable,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:104640:19"/>that it uſed <hi>to be granted at the inſtance and for the ſake of profeſſed Papiſts, that it is a greater favour than was granted the Church Party in the late Wars.</hi> I hoped thoſe old Sores had been healed, or however that we ſhould not take example of our Enemies ill uſage and cruelty to revenge the ſame upon them. The Papiſts were never for a Toleration of Proteſtants only, as we have it now, with excluſion to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and they were as much for putting the Penal Laws in execution at one time, as they were for To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration in another: ſo that they have been playing their game on both ſides, and both have been tricked by them. But with ſubmiſſion to the Irrefragable Reaſons of the Parliament in 1662. we have ſince ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently tryed other methods, and found them not only ineffectual but miſchievous, ſo that ſome ſuch Expedient as a Toleration was abſolutely neceſſary, either to prevent on one ſide the ſcandalous unſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full proſecution of weak and wilfull men, or on the other, the King's illegal diſpenſing with over ſevere Laws: I ſee the miſchief of a boundleſs and unlimited Toleration, but whether the miſchiefs of Perſecution, <hi>i. e.</hi> Extreme penalties for the ſake of Religion, be not greater, I leave to experience and the judgment of our Governours to determine. However it does not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Clergymen, who ſhould uſe the other methods of Tenderneſs and Perſwaſion more proper to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel and their Office, to grudge and repine at the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the State to thoſe who differ from them, and thereby diſcover their angry and revengefull Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and their good will to uſe other methods if it were in their power.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:104640:19"/>
2. I would never have a man that writes againſt all Alterations, at the ſame time propoſe any, eſpecially ſuch ſtrange ones as <hi>reading in our Churches the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles of</hi> Ignatius <hi>and</hi> Polycarp, <hi>or ſome</hi> ſelect Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>out of King</hi> Charles <hi>the Martyr's</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="(a)" place="margin">p. 26.</note>. For ſince he knows ſome People are greatly offended at the <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Leſſons, and would have nothing read in the Church but what is undoubtedly Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, it will look very odly to make ſuch a Propoſal to the Convocation at its next ſitting; and therefore I would deſire him not to move any ſuch thing, though perhaps the thing might take with ſome men if others were much againſt it, and out of mere ſpite to the deſign of Alterations they might clog the Bill with ſuch an Incumbrance. I do not intend to examine particular Alterations, but ſhall leave them to the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Convocation, and the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Nation, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Parliament, to agree and ſettle them as they ſhall think fit. I am for making ſome few Alterations, but am by no means for this of our Authour's propoſing, of reading <hi>Ignatius</hi> and <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carp,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in our Churches, though I like them almoſt as well as <hi>Tobit</hi> and <hi>his Dog,</hi> or <hi>Bell and the Dragon:</hi> however ſome queſtion whether they are all genuine.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Above all, I would adviſe our Authour when he writes again, never to make Compariſons between men, becauſe he knows, by the old Proverb, they are odious, and nothing can excuſe them, but when a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary defence calls for them.</p>
            <p>Thus though Dr. <hi>Jane</hi> be a very worthy perſon, and fills both the Profeſſor's and Prolocutor's Chair ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well and gracefully, yet why he and his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Clergy ſhould be in ſuch mighty Joy and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104640:20"/>becauſe he was choſen rather than Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> and look upon this as <hi>a good Omen for the good of the Church</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">p. 1.</note>, as if the choice of the other would have foreboded ſome miſchief to the Church; this is ſo unmannerly rude and reflecting that it requires the temper of that excellent Man to forgive it, who has done as much good to Religion and the Church, as half a Convocation, Prolocutor and all.</p>
            <p>But I perceive the bottom of the pique, our Author has a moſt ill opinion of Sermons on <hi>Week-days Lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> and the Dean has been a Preacher of ſuch, and has thereby provoked ſome, but taught more to Preach well and to Live well than any man perhaps ſince the Apoſtles; but why has our Authour and ſome others who are not much for Preaching on any day ſuch a ſpite againſt Sermons on the Week-days Lectures, why, he tells us, becauſe <hi>in thoſe many great Abſurdities ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Schiſm and Sedition are injected into the minds of the People</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">p. 26.</note>, and cannot they be as well injec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on Sunday Lectures, if Men have a mind, as well as on Week-days Lectures? nay, I know no abſolute Preſervative but that they may be injected in Sermons on Sunday morning, as well as at any other times, if the Preachers be very much inclined to it.</p>
            <p>I will by no means diſpute with our Author, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be not in the Countrey <hi>many Miniſters, who for their Learning may be without diſparagement compared with moſt of the City Miniſters</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">p. 15.</note>; that they may I'll aſſure him; and very much exceed them too, if he be a Countrey Miniſter himſelf, as I have two or three Reaſons beſides his Latine Sayings, which are far beyond the learning of moſt City Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to believe him to be. But why muſt he be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the Countrey and City Miniſters, like the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:104640:20"/>Countrey and City Mouſe, as <hi>to the great eaſe and pleaty of living</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">p. 37.</note>? I perceive he has been ſearching not only into their <hi>Veſtries, where they ſometimes tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> he ſays, <hi>till Prayers be ended;</hi> (he might have added, where they drink Sack too ſometimes after Sermon, which they don't in the Countrey) but into their very Kitchings, and ſo far as I know he might be for Reforming of thoſe, were he not againſt all Alterations and Amendments whatſoever. What brave Stories does he carry down, I warrant you, and tell his Neighbours in the Countrey of the City Miniſters plentifull eating and ſeldom preaching, <hi>having ſuch frequent Supplies, beſides Lectures and Readers</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note>, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the whole burthen lies upon them in the Countrey of ſtudying carefully and accurately penning their Sermons, and then preaching them in great Churches, beſides writing againſt Popery, and defending at all times the Cauſe of the Church and Religion. Further, <hi>It ought to be conſidered,</hi> he ſays, <hi>that a great part of the Countrey Miniſters have travelled ſome an hundred ſome near two hundred miles</hi> (but not the Apoſtolical way of footing it I ſuppoſe) <hi>to meet in Convocation for the benefit of the Clergy,</hi> and I hope the great good they have done there is a ſufficient reward for all their pains; <hi>and ſit ſometimes near the whole day in the depth of Winter,</hi> but they were hot enough they ſay for all this; and I pray where do the City Clergy of the Convocation ſit then? in a Veſtry, or ſome other warm place. One would think a man doated either with age or ſome other feebleneſs who would thus trifle and expoſe himſelf by ſuch drivelling and ridiculous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice: This is ſo below <hi>Don Quixot</hi> and <hi>Fur Praedeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> to which he mighty wittily compares the Authors of the two Letters, <hi>p.</hi> 56. but with an unaccountable
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:104640:21"/>impertinence and ſillineſs, that I can think of nothing for a <hi>New years gift</hi> for him but a Coat with long Sleeves and this Badge upon it, <hi>Nolumus mutare Leges Angliae.</hi> So I take my leave of him and wiſh him and his Neighbours a merry New Year.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENTS.</head>
            <p>THere is newly Printed <hi>a Large Folio Bible of a fair new Roman Letter</hi> with Annotations, and Parallel Scriptures or References (ſome Thouſands more than are in the <hi>Cambridge, Oxford,</hi> or any other Bible yet Extant.) To which is annexed, the Harmony of the Goſpels: As alſo a Reduction of the Jewiſh Weight, Coins and Meaſures to our Engliſh Standards: And a Table of the Promiſes in Scripture. In One intire Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, containing <hi>325</hi> Sheets. Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, Jonathan Robinſon,</hi> and <hi>Brabazon Aylmer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Allegiance Vindicated: or, the Takers of the New Oath of Allegiance to King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> juſtified; and the Lawfulneſs of taking it aſſerted, in its conſiſtency with our former Oaths; and alſo with the Doctrine of the Reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> concerning Non-reſiſtance and Paſſive Obedience. By a Divine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Printed for <hi>Brabazon Aylmer.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
